Guide to the Alfred von Kiderlen-Wächter Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alfred von Kiderlen-Wächter papers
1891-1912
MS 312
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6
Correspondence, writings, speeches, notes and clippings on European political affairs and biographical material of Kiderlen-Wächter, German diplomat and Secretary of State. The most significant and largest portion of his correspondence and notes is that to his mistress, Hedwig Heting Kypke. These papers form a veritable diary of his life and of events in the Foreign Office from 1891 to 1912. Other correspondents include Wilhelm II, Bethmann-Hollweg, von Bulow, Eulenburg-Hertefeld, Marschall von Bieberstein and Alfred Zimmerman.
Kiderlen-Wächter, Alfred von, 1852-1912
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Ernest Jackh, 1949.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Correspondence. II. Writings and Speeches. III. Subject File. IV. Biographical Material.
Scope and Contents
Series I CORRESPONDENCE (folders 1-162)
This series is divided into two parts: A. Letters to Hedwig (Heting) Kypke and B. General Correspondence.
The bulk of this series (folders 1-109) consists of Kiderlen-Wächter's letters to Hedwig (Heting) Kypke during the years 1891-1912. Following this there is a group of fourteen folders labelled "to Kypke-Excerpts," This material, written in diary or journal form, appears to be Kiderlen's thoughts and notes on various subjects and people. Following this is a group of folders containing correspondence with a range of other political figures. At the end of this series is a folder containing Hedwig Kypke's family correspondence from 1839-1901.
Series II WRITINGS AND SPEECHES (folders 163-172)
This series contains miscellaneous writings of Kiderlen-Wächter's: a sketchbook, excerpts of memoirs and poems, and his thesis. There are four folders containing descriptions of several of Kaiser Wilhelm's imperial excursions and finally several folders containing drafts of speeches honoring various people.
Series III SUBJECT FILE (folders 173-185)
This series contains correspondence and clippings of a political nature concerning England, German foreign policy, Morocco, Rumania, the Triple Alliance and Turkey. A partial list of the contents of the folders by subject is appended to this register.
Series IV BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL (folders 190-191)
This series contains material giving biographical data about Kiderlen-Wächter and also Hedwig Kypke. Several folders contain letters and anecdotal material about Kiderlen, his youth and family background. There is a book entitled Kypke Family Chronicle and a two-page biography of Hedwig Kypke.
Biographical / Historical
Entered German foreign office in 1879; appointed Secretary of State of the Foreign Office in 1910.
APPENDIX: PARTIAL LISTING OF FOLDER/CONTENTS IN SERIES III, SUBJECT FILE
England 1909
Kiderlen to Bethmann-Hollweg about German-English agreements account of a conversation between Bethmann- Hollweg and English ambassador Sir Goschen, 1909 Oct 14
Metternich's account of a conversation with Sir Grey, 1909 Oct 27 Kiderlen to Bethmann-Hollweg 1909 Nov 4
Account of a meeting between Bethmann-Hollweg (Sec. of State) von Shoen, and Sir Goschen, 1909 Nov 4
Telegram from Bethmann-Hollweg to German ambassador in London, 1909 Oct 27
Bethmann-Hollweg to Count Metternich, 1909 Nov 8
Flotow to Kiderlen, 1909 Nov 8
note from Bethmann-Hollweg to Kiderlen along with a note from Sir Goschen and (Sec. of state) von Schoen 1909 Nov 9
Telegram from Bethmann-Hollweg to Metternich, 1909 Nov 10
Kiderlen to Bethmann-Hollweg 1909 Nov 23
Sec. of State von Schoen to Kiderlen 1909 Nov 23
Draft of German-English peace treaty
England 1911
Kiderlen to Bethmann-Hollweg & Bethmann-Hollweg to Kiderlen about disarmament 1911 Feb 21
Jenisch to Kiderlen 1911 Aug 13
England 1912
Kaiser Wilhelm to Kiderlen about naval program 1912 Feb 24
Kiderlen's reply to Kaiser Wilhelm 1912 Feb 24
Bethmann-Hollweg's resignation to Kaiser Wilhelm 1912 Mar 6
Bethmann-Hollweg's speech in Reichstag, corrected by Kiderlen 1912 Mar 19
Proceedings of Reichstag 1912 Apr 22
Morocco 1911Concerning Casablanca
Cambon to Cruppi 1911 Jun 22
Weizsacker to Kiderlen 1911 Jul 8
Weizsacker to Kiderlen
Paris press reports about French-Spanish incident in Morocco Kiderlen to Bethmann-Hollweg 1911 Jul 17
Lehmann to Kiderlen
refusal by Kiderlen 1911 Jul 18
Bethmann-Hollweg to Kiderlen 1911 Jul 18
Kiderlen to Bethmann-Hollweg 1911 Jul 19
von Lindequist to Kiderlen 1911 Aug 7
Schwabach (?) to Kiderlen 1911 Aug 11
Hammann to Kiderlen 1911 Aug 17
German-French treaty vis a vis Morocco 1911 Sep 20
von Behr to Kiderlen 1911 Oct 5
Paul Schwabach to Kiderlen 1911 Oct 10
Sir Goschen to Kiderlen 1911 Nov 4
Cambon to Kiderlen 1911 Nov 5
Bethmann-Hollweg to Kiderlen about Lindequist
Kiderlen to King Carol 1911 Nov 9
Reichstag report on German-French treaty vis a vis Morocco
Morocco 1912
Bethmann-Hollweg to Kiderlen 1912 Jan (?)
Bethmann-Hollweg to Kiderlen 1912 Aug 26
Kiderlen to Bethmann-Hollweg 1912 Aug 29
Morocco folders 4-178 contains letters from various correspondents from 1910-1911
Rumania 1900
Beldiman to Kiderlen 1900 Jun 3
Rumania 1904
Kiderlen to King Carol 1904 Dec
Rumania 1905
Kiderlen's New Years greetings to King Carol
Rumania 1907
Sturdza to Kiderlen 1907 Jun 13
Sturdza to Kiderlen 1907 Jun 20
Sturdza to Kiderlen 1907 Jul 4
Rumania 1908
Costinescu to Kiderlen 1908 Jul 23
Jon Ghement to Kiderlen 1908 Jul 23
Kiderlen to Costinescu 1908 Jul 28
Kiderlen's New Year's greeting to the Crown prince 1908 Dec 28
Kiderlen's New Year's greetings to King Carol 1908 Dec
Rumania 1909
Bethmann-Hollweg to Kiderlen 1909 Aug 5
Kiderlen to Bethmann-Hollweg 1909 Aug
Kiderlen to Bethmann-Hollweg 1909 Sep 27
Kiderlen to Bethmann-Hollweg 1909 Sep 27
Kiderlen to Bethmann-Hollweg 1909 Sep 27
Kiderlen to Bethmann-Hollweg 1909 Sep 30
Kiderlen to Bethmann-Hollweg 1909 Oct 2
Kiderlen to Bethmann-Hollweg 1909 Oct 24
Romberg to Bethmann-Hollweg 1909 Nov 18
Kiderlen's New Year's greeting to the Crown prince 1909 Dec 29
Kiderlen's New Year's greeting to King Carol 1909 Dec 29
Rumania 1910
Kiderlen to Bratiano
Bratiano to Kiderlen telegram
Kiderlen's New Year's greeting to King Carol
to Kiderlen 1910 Apr 11
Sec. general of the French (?) foreign affairs ministry (?) to Kiderlen 1910 Jul 7
Telegram, Carl to Kiderlen 1910 Jun 30
Telegram, Bratiano to Kiderlen 1910 Jun 28
Kiderlen to Bratiano 1910 Jun 29
Telegram, orleano (?) to Kiderlen 1910 Jun 28
Telegram, Ionesco to Kiderlen 1910 Jun 28
Kiderlen to Bratiano 1910 Jun 29
Kiderlen to King (?) 1910 Jun 29
Rumania 1911
Kiderlen to King Carol 1911 Apr
Beldiman to Kiderlen (?) 1911 Aug 6
Rumania 1912
Kiderlen's New Year's greeting to King Carol
Kiderlen to King Carol 1912 Apr 15
Kiderlen to Richthofen
Triple Alliance 1910
Kiderlen to Bethmann-Hollweg 1910 Jan 31
Schonburg to Kiderlen, 1910 Jun 26
Aehrenthal to Kiderlen, 1910 Jul 2
Monts to Kiderlen, 1910 Sep 30
Triple Alliance 1911
Jagow to Kiderlen 1911 Dec 12
Bethmann-Hollweg to Kiderlen 1911 Dec 19
Triple Alliance 1912
Kiderlen to a Stuttgart friend (?) 1912 Jan 14
Jagow to Kiderlen 1912 Jan 15
Russian ambassador in Rome to Sazonow 1912 Mar 25
Russian ambassador in Rome to Sazonow 1912 Mar 25
Russian ambassador in Rome to Sazonow 1912 Mar 26
Triple Alliance 1911
Neratow to Benckendorff 1911 Nov 25
Neratow to Benckendorff 1911 Nov 27
Turkey 1899
Kiderlen from Copenhagen to Constantinople 1899 Jul 5
Turkey 1907
Kiderlen to Sultan Abdul Hamid
Turkish agreement
Newspaper clipping
Kiderlen to Sultan concerning Krupp arms 1907 Jun
Kiderlen to Sultan
Kiderlen concerning Bagdad railroad
Huguenin to Sultan
Huguenin to Sultan
Ferid Pascha to Kiderlen
Kiderlen concerning his talk with Sultan about the Konia concession (?) 1907 Sep 6
Ferid Pascha to Kiderlen about the Konia concession
von Pourtales to Kiderlen concerning Konia concession
Kiderlen about "the Holy Caravan" 1907 Sep 23; also about his audience with Sultan on 1907 Sep 27
Kiderlen's note about the Turkish representative
Turkey 1908
Concerning von Reval
Concerning visit of Coburg'schen princes
thank you telegram from prince Carl Edward
Kiderlen concerning visit of Abdul Rachman
Request from (?) Hassan Rami 1908 Aug 6
Request from Professor Wieting for Hassan Rami 1908 Aug 6
Notice from Italian agency 1908 Aug 14
Notice from Italian Agency 1908 Aug 17
Kiderlen to Bülow concerning alleged secret treaty between Austria and Turkey 1908 Aug 18
Relations between Turkey and Bulgaria 1908 Oct 16
Turkey 1909
Sec. of State Schoen to Kiderlen about conversation between the Bulgarian minister Malinow and the Russian envoy concerning Turkish-Bulgarian friendship, & relations between Bulgaria-Austria, and Bulgaria-Russia
Report from Military Attaché von Strumpel from Constantanople about an Austro-Turkish military conference 1909 Nov 11
Report from ambassador v. Tschirschky in Wien to Bethmann-Hollweg about a conversation between Graf Aehrenthal & Turkish ambassador in Berlin, Osman Nesami Pascha, about an Entente between Turkey, Austria-Hungary, and Rumania 1909 Nov 13
Report from German envoy in Sofia v. Romberg to Bethmann-Hollweg about an alleged secret treaty between Russia and Bulgaria
Turkey 1910
article about Kiderlen's comments on victory of gold marks from Budapest over Parisian Borse 1910 Sep 30
French reports concerning Turkish troop movements on Persian border as result of a German-Turkish accord reached at Marienbad 1910 Oct 20
Turkey 1911
telegram, from Bulow, German envoy In Sofia, about Turkish mobilization on Bulgarian border 1911 Oct 13
report from German ambassador in Constantinople, Marschall von Bieberstein, about military situation in Tripoli 1911 Nov 21
Neratoff's report from Petersburg about the wars in Tripoli
Turkey 1912
Note to Kiderlen from "deutschen Vaterlandsfreunden" concerning Asia Minor 1912 Nov 4
Kiderlen's speech in Bundesrat concerning German policy in Orient 1912 Nov 28
Telegram from Neratoff in Petersburg re: Russian policy in Persia 1912 Dec 10
Other Finding Aids
For a published description of collection contents and a listing of subject file folder contents, please consult the Published Description and Collection Inventory.
Europe; Germany -- Politics and government -- 1888-1918; Diplomats; Public officers; Kiderlen-Wächter, Alfred von, 1852-1912; Kypke, Hedwig, 1854-; Germany. Auswärtiges Amt
- Correspondence, Series I
  - To Hedwig (Heting) Kypke
    - 1891 November - 1893 December 30 (Box 1, Folder 1-20)
    - 1894 January 1 - 1896 October 22 (Box 2, Folder 21-36)
    - 1896 November 3 - 1898 December 31 (Box 3, Folder 37-50)
    - 1899 January 1 - 1900 May 31 (Box 4, Folder 51-65)
    - 1900 June 1 - 1902 December 30 (Box 5, Folder 66-78)
    - 1903 January 1 - 1907 September 29 (Box 6, Folder 79-91)
    - 1907 October 3 - November 6 (Box 7, Folder 92)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes telegram, 3 Oct, from Hofmarshall Freystedl [?] to Kiderlen and bulletin from Agence Fournier, 3 Oct Constantinople.
    - 1907 November 13 - 1908 December 31 (Box 7, Folder 93-98)
    - 1909 January 1 - January 31 (Box 7, Folder 99)
      Includes undated telegram from Carl [?] to Kiderlen and undated telegram from Elisabeth to Kiderlen [?] with letter of 4 Jan 09.
    - 1909 February 1 - June 30 (Box 7, Folder 100)
    - 1909 July 1 - July 29 (Box 7, Folder 101)
      Includes Theodore Weicher, Dieterich'sche Verlagsbuchhandlung, Leipzig, June; also letter 1909 Feb 29 Julius Lessee [?] to Kiderlen - Kiderlen to Kypke. TREAT FOLDER WITH CARE.
    - 1909 September 9 - 1910 January 24 (Box 7, Folder 102-103)
    - 1910 March 8 - July 31 (Box 7, Folder 104)
      Includes letter (draft?) to Chancellor, 14 Jun 1910, and letter Gustav Waschow, 3 Jun 1910.
    - 1910 August 7 - December 31 (Box 7, Folder 105)
      General note
      Includes New Year's greeting from Theodor Reuss to Kiderlen and draft of letter from Kiderlen to King of Rumania.
    - 1911 January 1 - May 31 (Box 7, Folder 106)
    - 1911 June 2 - December 31 (Box 8, Folder 107)
      Includes telegram from Elisabeth? and telegram forwarded to Kiderlen from Prince Ferdinand of Rumania.
    - 1912 January 1 - December 29 (Box 8, Folder 108-109)
  - To Kypke - Notes, Excerpts (Aufzeichnungen)
    - 1891 December 31 - 1907 December 13 (Box 8, Folder 110-123)
  - Correspondence with others
    - Beldiman, 1910 June 30 (Box 8, Folder 124)
    - Bethmann-Hollweg, 1910-1911, undated (Box 8, Folder 125)
    - Billo, 1897 November 6, 1909 July 22 (Box 8, Folder 126)
    - Cambon, 1910 Jul, undated (Box 8, Folder 127)
    - Carl (of Rumania) (Box 8, Folder 128)
    - Crown Prince (.?), 1910 June 30 (Box 8, Folder 129)
    - Diez, Hermann, 1911 August 3 (Box 8, Folder 130)
    - Eulenberg und Hertefeld, Fürst zu (Box 8, Folder 131)
    - Erzberger, M. (Box 8, Folder 132)
    - Flotow, 1910 January 7, undated (Box 8, Folder 133)
    - Gantes, E., n.y. September 9 (Box 8, Folder 134)
    - Georg, W., 1911 June 25, August 13 (Box 9, Folder 135)
    - Glasenapp (?) (Box 9, Folder 136)
    - Glaser, Carl, 1909 July 5 (Box 9, Folder 137)
    - Goschen, W. E., 1911 November 4 (Box 9, Folder 138)
    - Hammann, 1907 September 21 (Box 9, Folder 139)
    - Article about Otto Hammann by "Princeps" in Die Standarte (Box 9, Folder 140)
    - Hawersaat, 1900 February 12 (Box 9, Folder 141)
    - Helfferich, 1910 June 17, 1911 November 15 (Box 9, Folder 142)
    - Hoffmann, 1911 November 5 (Box 9, Folder 143)
    - Holstein, 1895? (Box 9, Folder 144)
    - Jagow, 1907 July 13 (Box 9, Folder 145)
    - Jionescv, Take, 1912 February 8 (Box 9, Folder 146)
    - Marschall von Bieberstein, 1908 July 21 (Box 9, Folder 147)
    - Minghetti, n.y. April 22 (Box 9, Folder 148)
    - Monts, A., 1909 January 6; n.y. December 20 (Box 9, Folder 149)
    - Pasha, Ibrahim Hakki, undated (Box 9, Folder 150)
    - Ratibor, 1910 July 4, July 5 (Box 9, Folder 151)
    - Raymund, 1909 June 12 (Box 9, Folder 152)
    - Rotenhan (?), 1897 July 21 (Box 9, Folder 153)
    - Schmidt, Hermann, 1911 July 25 (Box 9, Folder 154)
    - Stemrich, 1909 October - 1910 June 24 (Box 9, Folder 155)
    - Wilhelm, 1911 April 12 (Box 9, Folder 156)
    - Wilhelm, 1911 October 2, 1910 June 20 (Box 9, Folder 157)
    - Zimmermann, 1907 July 13 - 1912 (Box 9, Folder 158)
    - Kypke (?) - letter incomplete (Memoir?) (Box 9, Folder 159)
    - Misc. correspondence & clippings, 1908(?) (Box 9, Folder 160)
    - Congratulatory notes to Kiderlen-Wächter on his appointment to Staatssekretär (Box 9, Folder 161)
    - Kypke, Hedwig (Heting) - family correspondence, 1839-1901 (Box 9, Folder 162)
- Writings and speeches, Series II
  - Notebook (Sketchbook) (Box 9, Folder 163)
  - Memoirs-poems (Box 9, Folder 164)
  - Kiderlen's thesis Probearbeit (in French) on the Turkish-Greek War of 1821-1830, with letter (Box 9, Folder 165)
  - Travel Report (Kaiser's Nordlandsreise - summer 1892) (Box 9, Folder 166)
  - Travel Reports (Kaiser's trips), Undated, 1895 (Box 9, Folder 167)
  - Travel Reports, 1887, 1900, 1902, undated (Box 9, Folder 168)
  - Travel Report (Kaiser's trip on Hohenzollern, Nordlandsreise - summer?) (Box 9, Folder 169)
  - Speeches honoring Kaiser Wilhelm's birthday (Box 10, Folder 170)
  - Speech honoring King Carol of Rumania, 1910 (Box 10, Folder 171)
  - Speech honoring Franz Josef, undated (Box 10, Folder 172)
- Subject file, Series III
  General
  NOTE: For a partial listing of folder contents in Series III, SUBJECT FILE, see: Appendix.
  - Topical Documents and Correspondence - England, 1909-1911? (Box 10, Folder 173-174)
  - Topical Documents and Correspondence - England, Reichstags-Verhandlungen 1912 Apr w/news clippings (Box 10, Folder 175)
  - Miscellaneous notes and abstracts on German foreign policy, (various authors and recipients), 1908-1912 (Box 10, Folder 176)
  - Marokko (Morocco), 1908 - 1912 (Box 10, Folder 177-178)
  - Topical Documents and Correspondence - Rumania, 1900-1912, undated (Box 10, Folder 179-181)
  - Triple Alliance (Dreibund) and War in Tripoli, 1910-1912 (Box 10, Folder 182)
  - Topical Documents and Correspondence - Turkey, 1899-1912 (Box 10, Folder 183-185)
- Biographical material, Series IV
  - Anecdotes by Kypke about Kiderlen-Wächter, 1891-1912 (?) (Box 10, Folder 186)
  - Newspaper article (Schwäbischer Merkur), on Kiderlen-Wächter's family background, 1913 January 2 (Box 10, Folder 187)
  - Letters and notes re: Kiderlen's family and youth; anecdotes (Box 10, Folder 188)
  - Letter (memoir?) - incomplete re: Kiderlen (Box 10, Folder 189)
  - Book - Hedwig Kypke's family chronicle entitled, Kurze Chronik der Familie Kypke (1910) (Box 10, Folder 190)
  - Two-page typed biography of Hedwig Kypke (Box 10, Folder 191)
- Oversize materials
  - Kiderlen-Wachter, Alfred (von)
    - Newspapers
      - Berliner Tageblatt, 1919 October 11 (Box 11)
      - Volksstimme, 1911 September 26 (Box 11)
    - Aufzeichnungen, 1908-1912 (Box 11)
    - Documents, certificates, and degrees [Goettigen, Leipzig, Tubingen] (Box 11)